Now that we optimized our little demo application here,
Buradaki kk demo uygulamamz optimize ettik.
let me dive into that functional component versus stateful component or container component again.
Bu fonksiyonel bileen Wurzels'n durum bileenine veya konteyner bileenine tekrar girmeme izin verin.
So basically components defined with class which extend component which is one way of creating a component
Bu nedenle, temel olarak, bileen oluturmak iin bir yol olan bileeni genileten CLOS
and react and components which are just functions as all other components in this application are.
ile tanmlanan bileenler ve tepki ve sadece bu uygulamadaki dier tm bileenler gibi ilev gren bileenler vardr.
Now as I mentioned a lot in this course, you should try to create functional components as often as possible.
imdi bu derste oka bahsettiim gibi ilevsel bileenleri olabildiince sk oluturmaya almalsnz.
Why?
Niye ya.
Because these components have a narrow focus and a clear responsibility,
nk bu bileenler dar bir odaa ve net bir sorumlulua sahiptir.
they are only about presenting something, they are about rendering jsx and they contain some logic to
yaptmz gibi baz snflar ekleyerek GSX'i doru bir ekilde grntlemek iin baz mantklar ieriyorlar.
display the jsx correctly, for example by adding some css classes as we do here in the cockpit component.
Onlar sadece GSX oluturma ile ilgili bir ey sunmakla ykmldrler ve burada rnein kokpit bileeninde
They don't do much else
Onlar ok fazla ey yapmazlar.
and one thing they definitely don't do and they can't do is manage state.
Kesinlikle yapmadklar ve yapamayacaklar ey, devleti ynetmektir.
And I mention a lot that the reason why we have this separation is that we want to have a few places
Ve oka sz verdim ki, bu ayrlmann nedeni, uygulamanzda,
in our application where the application state does change, this makes sure your application stays maintainable
uygulama durumunun deitii birka yer olmas gerektiidir; bu, uygulamanzn bydke
even as it grows. Because the more your application grows, the harder it becomes to manage state because
bile bakml olmasn salar; uygulamanz daha fazla byrse devleti ynetmek olur;
if you manage state in every single component, it is super hard to track where you edited this list of
nk her bir bileen iinde eyaleti ynetirseniz, bu yeni yayn oluturduunuz kiilerin
persons, where you created this new post.
listesini nerede dzenlediinizi izlemek ok zor.
If you get a few containers where you do that and where you then simply pass state and hand the rest down via
Bunu yaptnz birka konteynr alrsanz ve daha sonra basite devlete geip geri kalann elimizden gelenin
props
altna verelim.
this is much easier to handle because you can always see in the end, the state gets changed here in the
Bu ele alnmas daha kolaydr, nk burada her zaman grebileceiniz gibi Aptera'da olduu gibi
app.js file
burada devlet deiir.
And we distribute references to the functions which edited via props but all the other components
Ve bir pervane ancak dier tm bileenlerin devleti deitiremeyeceini
are not able to change state.
dzenleyen ilevlere referanslar datyoruz.
This is one of the core foundations of a good react application,
Bu, iyi bir yeniden bavuru ileminin temel dayanaklarndan biridir.
use the class based components as little as possible but of course don't be afraid of using them if it
bileenleri olabildiince az kullann ancak elbette mantklysa bunlar kullanmaktan korkmayn.
makes sense.
Snf temelli
If you get a central point in your application and a good split typically are multiple features,
Bavurunuzda merkezi bir nokta bulursanz ve iyi bir blnme genellikle birden ok zelliktir.
So for example if you have a blog feature and authentication feature in your app, then the root components
rnein, uygulamanzda bir engelleme zellii ve kimlik dorulama zellii varsa, bu zelliklerin kk
of these features might very well be containers which manage the state for that feature area and you
bileenleri, o zellik alan iin durumu yneten konteynerler olabilir ve bunu, bu zellik alanna girdiimizde
will see this in action throughout this course when we dive into the bigger course project.
skorlar iin geerli olduunu greceksiniz. Daha byk ders projesi.
But all other components as mentioned often should be functional components, I'll also dive into one important
Ancak bahsedilen bileenlerin ou zaman ilevsel bileenler olmal, devlet varlnn yan sra nemli
difference besides the existence of state and the availability of methods which you have in class based
bir farka dalm ve snf temelli bileenlerde sahip olduunuz yntemlerin yetenei ile ilgilenmek
components.
zorundayz.
I'll dive into one other important difference between class components and functional components in the next
Bir sonraki derslerde snf bileenleri ve ilevsel bileenler arasndaki nemli bir
lectures
farka dalacam.
and that would be the lifecycle of a component. Before diving into the lifecycle,
Ve yaam dngsne dalmadan nce bir bileenin yaam dngs olurdu.
let's compare stateless and stateful components again. Just to bring this back into mind, stateful
Devleti daha az karlatmz halde, devlet bileenlerini yeniden gzden geirelim, bunu yalnzca tam bileenlerin zihin durumuna getirmek iin
components
tekrar edelim.
also referred to as containers and stateless components differ
Ayrca konteynerler ve devlet daha az bileen olarak anlacaktr farkldr.
by the fact that stateful components are created with the class word and extend component whereas
Aslnda, devletin tam bileenleri Klasky szc ve uzants bileeni ile oluturulurken,
stateless ones are just functions which receive props.
devlet daha az olanlar yalnzca sahne alm olan ilevlerdir.
Now import differences are of course the access to state
Artk ithalat farkllklar elbette devlete eriimdir.
and does this is new, the existence of lifecycle hooks. In stateful containers, we can access state and we
Ve bu yeni bir yaam dngs varl, devlete eriebildiimiz duruma zg kaplarda kanca yapar
can implement lifecycle hooks, I'll come back to what that is in the next lecture. Stateless components
ve yaam dngs kancalarn uygulayabilir veya bir sonraki ders durumunda geri dnebiliriz, son
neither have access to the state nor can they implement lifecycle hooks,
bileen bir devlete asla eriemez veya yaam dngs kancalarn uygulayamazlar.
and if we want to access the state and props, in stateful containers, we do this via the this keyword
Ve eyalete ve devletlere ait tam konteynrlardaki sahne rnlerine erimek istiyorsak, bunu neden bu
this.state.xy, this.props.xy, and in stateless components, we do this via just props.xy, we receive
anahtar kelimeyi eklemelisin bu durumu X Y bu pervane x y ve devletimizin son bileeninde yaptmz gibi, biz sadece sahne yelpazemiziz x y bir
props as an argument.
argman olarak sahne alyoruz.
And as mentioned often, only use stateful components if you need to manage state or access lifecycle
ihtiya duyarsanz, yalnzca devlet tam bileenlerini kullann, tm Aberg durumlarda durumunu daha az bileenleri kullann.
hooks, use stateless components in all other cases.
Ve belirtildii gibi devleti ynetmek veya genel kullanma hazr yaam dngs kancalarna
And just because we never did it, I want to highlight is this.props.xy thing in stateful components.
Ve bunu vurgulamak istemediimiz bir ey yapmamamz, devletin tam bileenleri iindeki sahne yuvas eyidir.
If we consider our only stateful component we have here, it doesn't even use props,
Eyaletimizin tamamna sahip olduumuz tek unsuru gz nne alrsak, burada sahip olduumuz, sahne bile kullanmyor.
it only use state but it would have access to props too
Yalnzca bir devlet kullanyor ancak sahtelere de eriebiliyordu.
and I can demonstrate this to you.
Ve ben bunu size gsterebilirim.
Let me pass some props right from the index.js
Birka sahne dizinden geireyim.
file,
Evet.
let me pass a title prop here which can just be a string where I will say relevant persons. Now this
burada ilgili peruses syleyeceim bir dize olabilir Sadece bir kapsayc olan Access uygulamamzn bal olabilir.
can be the title of our application, in app.js which is a container
Bana bir alfabe pabucu iletmeme izin verin,
we can still access props, it's not like it doesn't have access to props. Here,
Hala pervanelere eriebiliriz, buradaki sahne alanna eriimi yok gibi deil.
we want to maybe pass this on to the cockpit to display it there.
Onu orada gstermek iin belki de bunu kokpite gtrmek istiyoruz.
So let's define a new title there, a new property there, maybe the app title,
Dolaysyla, yeni bir balk tanmlayalm orada uygun bir balk olabilecek yeni bir mlk var.
do not confuse it with the prop we're about to pass on.
Onu gemek zere olduumuz pervane ile kartrmayn.
And now we know that there is this
Ve imdi merdivenlerin olduunu biliyoruz.
title property available in our app component because we set it here in the index.js file.
Balk mlkmz, uygulama bileenimizde byk bir su gbei olsun, nk burada Jaspal dizinde syledik.
Now of course, we can't access it like this,
phesiz elbette buna u ekilde eriemiyoruz.
we can't access props title because props would be undefined variable here.
Pervane'nin balna eriemiyoruz nk pervane burada tanmsz olacakt.
We're inside a render method
leme yntemimizin iinde.
and inside this method, we never defined props and this method also doesn't receive props as an argument,
Ve bu yntem iinde hibir zaman sahne bulamadk ve bu yntem de pervaneleri bir argman olarak
so props is undefined here.
almaz, bu nedenle pervane burada tanmszdr.
But the class itself has a props property because we extend component
Ancak snfn kendisi bir pervanenin mlkne sahiptir, nk bileeni geniletiyoruz.
And just as we have access to a set state method which we never defined ourselves,
Tpk kendimiz bulamadmz belirli bir devlet yntemine eriebildiimiz gibi.
we also have access to a props property we never defined ourselves.
Hepimizin kendimizi tanmlamadmz uygun bir mlke eriebiliyoruz.
It's given to us and populated by react and we can therefore access this.props like this
Bize verildi ve tepki gsterdi; dolaysyla bu sahneye bu ekilde eriebiliriz.
and this case, we simply pass it on
Ve bu davay basite aktaracaz.
but of course we could also output it here in this template.
Ancak elbette bu ablonu buradan da ktrabiliriz.
But since we pass it on,
Ama bunu getiimizden beri.
I'll now go to the cockpit and handle this brand new property maybe here to output it to your props
imdi kokpite gideceim ve burada yeni bir mlk ele alacam, burada
app title. In here again, just using props because we do receive props as an element here
bir sahne alm yapmak iin sahne aletini kullanarak buradaki sahne prodksiyon nitesine kt.
With one curly brace though. Props is just the argument we receive for this function, passed into it automatically
Bir meslektam sahteleri justi argman olarak desteklese de, imdi tm dosyalar kaydetmek ve bavurumuza geri dnersek,
by react. If we save all files now and go back to our application, you'll see relevant persons as the new title
tepki olarak kendisine otomatik olarak geirilen ilev bozukluuna kavutuumuz iin burada alakal ve yeni bir balk
we're seeing here because now we're setting this in the index.js file and we pass it down
greceiz nk imdi biz Bunu bir sonraki satran dosyasnda ayarlarsak, onu geeriz.
and as you can see, we got props in our container queue,
Ve grdnz gibi konteyner sramzda tropsaller elde ediyoruz.
We didn't use it before because we never received something before
Daha nce hi kullanmadk nk daha nce kullanmadk.
but if you want to use props here, use it with this.props just as you use this.state because you're in
Ancak burada sahne seti kullanmak isterseniz, tpk bu snf kullandnzdan bu
a class here,
sahnede kullann.
You're not in a function, you are not receiving props and state as arguments here.
Burada, argmanlar olarak sahne ve devlet almadnz bir ilevi bulunmuyorsunuz.